<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Richard Placide</title>
 <link href="http://richardplacide.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://richardplacide.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2013-10-06T18:22:30-04:00</updated>
 <id>http://richardplacide.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name>Richard Placide</name>
 </author>
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>A Fresh New Start With Jekyll</title>
   <link href="http://richardplacide.github.io/2013/07/30/fresh-start-jekyll/"/>
   <updated>2013-07-30T08:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://richardplacide.github.io/2013/07/30/fresh-start-jekyll</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In a way I&#39;m I think I am lucky to have experienced the what are to my the three main stages of web development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Static web page&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first stage, which started way before I discovered it, is of course building static web pages. Fortunately I started web development when Dreamweaver was already a full fledged product which eased the chore of creating and maintainig dozens if not hundred of html pages. It was not a pleasant experience though and I first ran into major headaches when I had to take a 10+-years-old website with several hundred html and images files. Learning the structure was a hard task especially since I didn&#39;t have the contact of the web developper who had worked on it.
Fortunaly, my mssion consisted precisely in moving away from this maintenance-hell to a modern content management system. It is safe to say that very few web developpers would regret this era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Content Management Systems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first content management system I learned was Joomla circa 2006. Interestingly I inherited the huge static website two years later. After Joomla I tested Drupal, that made a great impression on me and also the unavoidable WordPress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2008, my mission consisted in moving away from the html website to a new typo3 solution. I had no experience with that CMS and since we had established a long selection process I was allowed to try and test alternative solution like Drupal and ... Django. Although a web framework like Django or Rails can be a perfect fit for a large website I soon realized that this would be too much development for our needs and we wanted to fall into the same trap: having a web solution that was either hard to maintain or that required a specific skillset that the organisation was not willing to hire anyway. Drupal had my preference but sadly, givn the short time I was not able to master it to the point where I could counter the strong argument in favor of Typo3. Indeed this large CMS was the preferred choice of our IT department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 5 years of using typo3, I am particularly frustrated with a needlessly complex piece of software compared to our needs. I might be saying more about me than about Typo3 but after 5 years I&#39;m still not confortable with it and I keep getting biten by it. On the other hand, I discoverd and enjoyed WordPress a bit later and it is a plateform that I am quite at ease with. As a matter of fact WordPress is the go-to solution that (like a lot of people) recommend without any hesitation. I will go as far I saying that most people should actually start by evaluation WordPress and then move to something else if it doesn&#39;t fit the bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Static sites generators&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lead us to July 2013, when I finally got my hand on Jekyll. I had been aware of the concept of static sites generators but at the time I didn&#39;t really understand how useful the concept could be. The only solution I gave a cursory look to was Hyde (because at the time I was in my python-or-nothing mindset). If only I had known that ruby doesn&#39;t really matter when it comes to using Jekyll I might have given this number one solution the closer look it deserves. It is interesting to note that it is because I got a bit more familiar with ruby (mostly through rails) that I was willing to give Jekyll a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is the fuss about with sites generators ? In a word: they&#39;re awesome! But that is a bit too simplistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me they are the near perfect middle ground between content management systems, classic sites and even web frameworks. With them, the web developper retains a significant amount of flexibility and ease of content publishing from the cms world while benefiting from the performance (no server side code, no database) and security advantages (again no server side code and no database) of static websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great starting point is Garry Welding&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://in-the-attic.com/2013/01/04/building-a-blog-using-jekyll-bootstrap-and-github-pages-a-beginners-guide/&quot;&gt;beginner&#39;s guide&lt;/a&gt; that has the benefit of coming with a forkable blog example that works perfectly out of the box. This blog is based on Garry&#39;s great work.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Assuming A Web Presence</title>
   <link href="http://richardplacide.github.io/2013/07/22/assuming-a-web-presence/"/>
   <updated>2013-07-22T08:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://richardplacide.github.io/2013/07/22/assuming-a-web-presence</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s never too late to start assuming a web presence, and it is as important as ever.
Having your own web outlet is not just about existing on the inter-connected world it is also about controlling the message; your message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For how people and organisations perceive you and your personal brand is increasingly dependant on what can be found on the web. Having your own blog and social media accounts is one way to influence what exists about you on the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting up a blog or a website is the first step towards achieving more control your personal brand and image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/assuming-a-web-presence/shangtower.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Shangai Towers&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>